<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="16SPAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1054360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6D7133AF935A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="5414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS  Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. Costumes, set pieces, filming equipment and other items relating to film, television and video are on permanent display. Exhibitions include ''Behind the Screen,'' a permanent display with more than 1,000 artifacts that illustrate the production, marketing and exhibition of moving images. ''Monk's Cafe,'' the set of the diner where much of the Seinfeld sitcom took place, includes costumes and scripts. Through August 1999. Daily screenings in Tut's Fever Movie Palace on weekends at 1, 2, 3 and 4 P.M.; weekdays at 1, 2:30 and 4 P.M. Through Dec. 25, episodes of the 12-part ''Buck Rogers'' serial (1940) starring Buster Crabbe. A retrospective of films by the director John Waters, though Nov. 1. Tomorrow: ''Mondo Trasho'' (1969), at 2 P.M., preceded by the short film ''The Diane Linkletter Story'' (1970); ''Polyester'' (1981), at 4:30. Sunday: ''Multiple Maniacs'' (1970), at 2 P.M.; ''Female Trouble'' (1974), at 4 P.M. ''Computer Space '98'' is a continuing exhibition of arcade games and contemporary home-entertainment software that visitors can play. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. All activities are free with museum admission unless indicated otherwise. Admission: $8.50; the elderly and students, $5.50; ages 5 to 18, $4.50; 4 and under, free. Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS  Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. Costumes, set pieces, filming equipment and other items relating to film, television and video are on permanent display. Exhibitions include ''Behind the Screen,'' a permanent display with more than 1,000 artifacts that illustrate the production, marketing and exhibition of moving images. ''Monk's Cafe,'' the set of the diner where much of the Seinfeld sitcom took place, includes costumes and scripts. Through August 1999. Daily screenings in Tut's Fever Movie Palace on weekends at 1, 2, 3 and 4 P.M.; weekdays at 1, 2:30 and 4 P.M. Through Dec. 25, episodes of the 12-part ''Buck Rogers'' serial (1940) starring Buster Crabbe. A retrospective of films by the director John Waters, though Nov. 1. Tomorrow: ''Mondo Trasho'' (1969), at 2 P.M., preceded by the short film ''The Diane Linkletter Story'' (1970); ''Polyester'' (1981), at 4:30. Sunday: ''Multiple Maniacs'' (1970), at 2 P.M.; ''Female Trouble'' (1974), at 4 P.M. ''Computer Space '98'' is a continuing exhibition of arcade games and contemporary home-entertainment software that visitors can play. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. All activities are free with museum admission unless indicated otherwise. Admission: $8.50; the elderly and students, $5.50; ages 5 to 18, $4.50; 4 and under, free. Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY, Audubon Terrace, Broadway at 155th Street, Washington Heights. The society has the most extensive coin collection in North America; its library is open to the public. On permanent display is ''American Numismatic Design, 1892-1922,'' which includes all coins issued during this period. Also on view is ''The World of Coins,'' a history since 600 B.C. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 4 P.M. Information: (212) 234-3130.  HISPANIC SOCIETY OF AMERICA, Audubon Terrace, Broadway at 155th Street, Washington Heights. A museum dedicated to Hispanic culture, with fine and decorative arts of the Iberian Peninsula, from prehistory to the present. Exhibitions: ''Learning the Art of Embroidery: 19th-Century Spanish Samplers,'' examples of that period's embroidery and lace, through November. ''Spain/America, Circa 1840-1920: Small Oils by American and Spanish Artists,'' through Dec. 19. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 4 P.M.; closed holidays. Free. Information: (212) 926-2234.  MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, 1220 Fifth Avenue, at 103d Street. The museum collects, preserves and presents materials related to the history of New York City. ''New York Begins: A Rare Drawing of New Amsterdam (circa 1650),'' a recently discovered watercolor of Manhattan as it appeared 25 years after its founding by the Dutch, through Nov. 29. Other exhibitions include: ''Half Past Autumn: The Art of Gordon Parks,'' a retrospective of works by the photojournalist, filmmaker, novelist and musician; through Nov. 1. ''Forum: Image and Reality in the World of Filmmaking,'' featuring filmmakers who will pay tribute to the pioneering work of Mr. Parks, including Tammi Gold, Al Santana and Dorothy Thigpen, Sunday at 3 P.M. Every Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. through Nov. 1, gallery talks on Mr. Parks's creative works. His one-hour 1986 autobiographical film, ''Moments Without Proper Names,'' will be shown continuously in the first-floor video room. ''Broadway! The Great White Way in 1898,'' a year in which 170 shows opened on Broadway; through Jan. 31. ''A Float for All Seasons: New York's Ethnic Parades,'' with handmade objects and color photographs by Martha Cooper; through Jan. 10. ''The New Metropolis: A Century of Greater New York, 1898-1998'' examines the people and places of the city as it celebrates the centennial of the consolidation of the five boroughs; through Jan. 3. ''A Century of Cityscapes: Paintings of New York City, 1800-1900''; Through Feb. 7. Hours: Tuesdays, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. for registered groups only; Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sundays, noon to 5 P.M.; closed holidays. Suggested admission: $5; the elderly, students and children, $4; families, $10. Information: (212) 534-1672.  MUSEUM OF JEWISH HERITAGE: A LIVING MEMORIAL TO THE HOLOCAUST, 18 First Place, at West Street and Battery Place, Battery Park City. Artifacts, documents, photographs, videos and film clips are included in exhibitions on the Holocaust and on Jewish life before and after World War II. Exhibitions include ''Jewish Life a Century Ago,'' with memorabilia from Jewish rituals and celebrations in Europe in the early 1900's; ''War Against the Jews,'' detailing events from 1933 to 1945, and ''Jewish Renewal,'' focusing on life after the Holocaust. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursdays, 9 A.M. to 8 P.M.; Fridays and the eves of Jewish holidays, 9 A.M. to 2 P.M.; closed Saturdays. Admission: $7; students and the elderly, $5; 5 and under, free. Some same-day tickets are available at the museum; because of heavy attendance, tickets may be purchased in advance through Ticketmaster: (212) 307-4007. Information: (212) 968-1800.  NEW YORK CITY FIRE MUSEUM, 278 Spring Street, SoHo. In a renovated 1904 firehouse, a collection of fire-related art and artifacts from the 18th century to the present, including a fire engine, hose wagons, hats, toys, paintings, memorabilia and hand-drawn pumpers. Also, an exhibition, ''Fire Marks: Emblems of Insurance,'' features 18th- and 19th-century British and American fire marks from the museum's collection. Insurance agencies gave bonuses to firefighters when they saved the premises of a policyholder. The decorative emblems were used to distinguish policyholders from the uninsured. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Suggested admission: $4 for adults; $2 for students and the elderly; $1 for children under 12. Information: (212) 691-1303.  NEW YORK TRANSIT MUSEUM, Boerum Place and Schermerhorn Street, downtown Brooklyn. Harvey R. Zipkin's photographs of passengers on New York City buses, on view through today. ''Steel, Stone and Backbone''  traces construction of the subway system from 1900 to 1925, with photographs, construction tools, films and other objects; ''Ceramic Ornamentation,'' a look at the mosaics, tiles and terra cotta used to adorn subway stations from 1904 to the present, and ''Here to There: Signs for Moving Around Underground,'' a display of more than 100 subway signs, continuing. Also on view are 19 restored subway cars from 1903 to 1960. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 P.M.; closed Mondays and holidays. Admission: $3; the elderly and ages 6 to 17, $1.50; 5 and under, free. On Wednesdays from noon to 4 P.M., admission is free for the elderly. Information: (718) 243-8601.  STATEN ISLAND INSTITUTE OF ARTS AND SCIENCES, 75 Stuyvesant Place, St. George. Cultural museum and library with artistic, scientific and environmental collections. ''1998 Biennial Juried Art Exhibition,'' works selected from 225 artists around the country. Through March 7. On display: ''East/West: Traditions in Christian Art,'' including 23 Russian icons painted by the Rev. John Walsted of Staten Island; through Jan. 3. A slide show and lecture on the Byzantine Period with Linda Butti, tomorrow at 10:30 A.M. Tickets: $15; $10 for members. The Family Gallery Hands-On Exhibit features specimens, art, artifacts and activities. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: $2.50; students and the elderly, $1.50; children under 12, $1.25. Information: (718) 727-1135.</p>
        <p>ON THE STREET</p>
        <p>EARTH SCHOOL FALL FAIR, Tompkins Square Park Baseball Park, 10th Street and Avenue A, East Village. Tomorrow, noon to 5 P.M.  FOURTH STREET UNITED METHODIST FESTIVAL, West Fourth Street, between Avenue of the Americas and University Place, West Village. Tomorrow, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.  VANDERBILT Y.M.C.A. SECOND AVENUE FESTIVAL, Second Avenue, from 46th to 56th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.  THIRD AVENUE FALL FESTIVAL, from 23d to 33d Streets, Kips Bay. Sunday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.  SEVENTH UPPER BROADWAY FALL FESTIVAL, Broadway, 110th to 116th Streets, Morningside Heights. Tomorrow, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.  AUTUMN CRAFTS ON COLUMBUS, Columbus Avenue, 77th to 81st Streets, Manhattan. Tomorrow and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 5:30 P.M. Sponsored by the American Arts and Crafts Alliance.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
        <p>KURT STEINER CROSS-COUNTRY 5K AND 1.5-MILE YOUTH RUN, Van Cortlandt Park, 252d Street and Broadway, the Bronx. The five-kilometer race begins Sunday at 11:30 A.M., followed by the 1.5 youth run at 12:30 P.M. Sponsored by the New York Road Runners Club. Registration on race day; fee: $3; $2 for youth run. Information: (212) 860-4455.</p>
        <p>WALKING TOURS</p>
        <p>''MERCHANTS, MAYORS AND MAGNIFICENCE: MANHATTAN'S CIVIC CENTER,'' lower Manhattan. A tour that includes the city's 1812 City Hall, the Municipal Building, the courts of Foley Square, the Woolworth Building and the former Newspaper Row. Today at 11 A.M. at St. Paul's Chapel, Broadway, between Fulton and Vesey Streets. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Tickets, $10 ($8 for students, the elderly and society members). Information: (212) 935-3960.  ''THE GRAND TOUR,'' covering the architecture and history of the East 42d Street area in Manhattan, including the Chrysler, Chanin and Mobil Buildings, the Bowery Savings Bank and Pershing Square. Meets Fridays at 12:30 P.M. at the Whitney Museum at Philip Morris, Park Avenue at 42d Street. Free. Sponsored by the Grand Central Partnership. Information: (212) 883-2468.  ''SOHO.'' A walk through the cast-iron buildings, shops and galleries of SoHo. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. at the southeast corner of Houston Street and Broadway. Fee: $10. Sponsored by ''I'll Take Manhattan Walking Tours.'' Information: (732) 270-5277.  ''PRESERVING THE MODERNS: 1940-1965; CULTURAL CUL-DE-SAC: LINCOLN CENTER, CATALYST FOR URBAN RENEWAL.'' A walk from Columbus Circle to Lincoln Square. Meets tomorrow at 11 A.M. at the Maine Monument, northeast corner of Central Park West and 59th Street. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Fee: $15; $12 for members of the Municipal Art Society. Information: (212) 935-3960.  ''THE GENIUS AND ELEGANCE OF GRAMERCY PARK,'' a tour of an exclusive  Manhattan neighborhood that was once a marshland. Meets Sunday at 1 P.M. at the Gramercy Park Hotel, Lexington Avenue and 21st Street. Fee: $12. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours of New York. Information: (212) 242-5762.  ''HIDDEN TREASURES OF CHINATOWN'' touches on the early careers of Al Jolson and Irving Berlin, who started out as singing waiters at the Chatham Cafe, which has been replaced by the Chinatown Post Office. The tour also includes a visit to the 18th-century mansion of Edward Mooney on the Bowery. Meets tomorrow at 10:30 A.M. at the northwest corner of the Bowery and Canal Street. Sponsored by Dr. Phil: New York Talks and Walks. Fee: $10. Information: (888) 377-4455.  ''TAKE A WALK ON THE WILD SIDE AT THE ALLEY POND PARK TULIP FOREST,'' Queens. A look at the topographical history of the park. Tomorrow at 10 A.M. Sponsored by the Alley Pond Environmental Center. Fee: $7; $5 for members of the Environmental Center. Registration: (718) 229-4000.  ''HISTORIC PUBS AND TAVERNS'' visits 10 pubs, including the White Horse Tavern and Chumley's. Tomorrow at 5:30 P.M. Fee: $10; refreshments not included. Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Reservations required: (212) 465-3331.  ''NEW YORK BEGINS WALKING TOUR,'' lower Manhattan. A walking tour that highlights the area during the Dutch and English colonial periods, with stops at the Peter Minuit flagpole, the sites of the Stadt Huys/Lovelace Tavern and an early Jewish community and other locations. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M at Trinity Church, Trinity Place. Sponsored by the Museum of the City of New York. Fee: $10; $8 for students, the elderly and members of the Museum of the City of New York. Information: (212) 534-1672.  THE THEATER DISTRICT: ''IT'S GOING TO BE A BUMPY NIGHT: A CURMUDGEON'S-EYE-VIEW OF THE THEATER DISTRICT'' passes historic theaters and classic movie and television sites from 42d Street to the Stage Delicatessen. Saturdays and Sundays at 10 A.M. Fee: $10. Sponsored by New York Curmudgeon Tours. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 629-8813.  HARLEM. A tour that will include stops at a row house occupied by Marcus Garvey in 1918; the Langston Hughes house on East 127th Street; the Schomburg Center for Black Culture and Research, and Harlem Hospital. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. at 306 Lenox Avenue (Malcolm X Boulevard), at 125th Street. Fee: $10. Sponsored by Radical Walking Tours. Information: (718) 492-0069.  ''SEINFELD AND HIS NEIGHBORS,'' Upper West Side. Visits sites related to the sitcom, including the television homes of the main characters. Tomorrow at 11:30 A.M. and 1:30 P.M. and Sunday at noon and 2:30 P.M. Fee: $10. Sponsored by Gotham Walk. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 629-1886.  ''IMMIGRANT NEW YORK.'' A multiethnic walking tour of the Jewish East Side, Chinatown, Little Italy and other cultural neighborhoods. Stops include the African burial ground, Mulberry Bend and sites associated with Sun Yat-sen, Mother Cabrini and Abraham Cahan. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. in front of City Hall. Fee: $10; students and the elderly, $8. Sponsored by Big Onion Walking Tours. Information: (212) 439-1090.  ''THE TRIBECA YOU NEVER KNEW.'' A historical walking tour of a commercial district that developed into a residential area and a center for artists. Tomorrow at 2:30 P.M. and Sunday at noon. Fee: $12. Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Reservations required: (212) 465-3331.  ''COME ON HOME TO BED-STUY,'' Brooklyn. An annual tour of historic brownstones. Meets tomorrow at 10:30 A.M. at Boys High School, 832 Gardner Taylor Boulevard, at Putnam Avenue. Fee: $10 in advance, $12 on the day. Sponsored by Brownstoners of Bedford-Stuyvesant. Information: (718) 574-1979.  ''PUBS AND POLTERGEISTS,'' a tour of the West Village with stops at two of its oldest taverns. Meets tomorrow at 6 P.M. in front of the Church of St. Luke-in-the-Fields, at the corner of Hudson and Grove Streets. Fee: $10, not including drinks and tips. Sponsored by Street Smarts N.Y. Information: (212) 969-8262.  ''MARVELOUS MURRAY HILL,'' a tour that includes the Union League Club, the Morgan Library and the former home of Franklin D. Roosevelt. Tomorrow at 1 P.M. Fee: $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Information and meeting place: (212) 265-2663.  ''GREENWICH VILLAGE: NEW YORK'S LEFT BANK,'' a tour of the streets that have been home to such writers and artists as Eugene O'Neill, Edna St. Vincent Millay, Edgar Allan Poe and Edward Hopper. Meets Saturdays at noon at the Washington Arch, Washington Square. Through Dec. 26. Sponsored by Mainly Manhattan Tours. Fee: $10. Information: (212) 755-6199.  ''GHOSTS ON BROADWAY,'' Manhattan. A tour past some of the ''haunted'' spots in Times Square, including hotels and theaters. Meets tomorrow at 2 P.M. in front of the Belasco Theater, 44th Street off Avenue of the Americas. Fee: $10. Sponsored by Street Smarts N.Y. Information: (212) 969-8262.  ''TERRIFIC TURTLE BAY,'' Manhattan. A neighborhood stroll in the East 40's, passing through the United Nations headquarters and Turtle Bay Gardens. Tomorrow at 3 P.M. Fee: $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Information: (212) 265-2663.  ''THE LOWER EAST SIDE: THE ROAD LESS TRAVELED.'' A tour that covers a rarely explored section of the Lower East Side, examining the settlement house movement and the oldest Ashkenazic synagogue in America. Meets on Sunday at 1 P.M. at the southeast corner of Allen and Houston Streets. Fee: $15; Municipal Art Society Members, $12. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Information: (212) 935-3690.  ''DESTINATION: MOTT HAVEN, REPOSITORY OF THE OLD BRONX.'' A walk through an area rich with residential, industrial and institutional architecture. Sunday at 1:30 P.M. Fee: $18. Sponsored by the 92d Street Y. Meeting place and information: (212) 996-1100.  JEWISH HARLEM. A walk past the synagogues, row houses and theaters in Central Harlem, from 110th to 125th Streets. Sunday at 1 P.M. Fee: $20. Sponsored by the 92d Street Y. Meeting place and reservations: (212) 996-1100.  ''JACKSON HEIGHTS, EMBLEM OF AN ENGLISH GARDEN SUBURB,'' Queens. An architectural walk past apartment buildings, gardens, golf courses and tennis courts. Sunday at 1 P.M. Fee: $18. Meeting place and information: (212) 996-1100.  HISTORIC GRAVESEND, Brooklyn. A five-mile hike past historic buildings. Meets Sunday at 2 P.M. in front of Republic National Bank, Kings Highway and McDonald Avenue. Sponsored by the Outdoors Club. Fee: $3. Information: (718) 252-2161.  HASIDIC BROOKLYN. A tour that combines a bus ride from Manhattan with a walking tour of a Hasidic neighborhood in Brooklyn with stops at synagogues, a bakery and a library. Leaves Sundays at 9:30 A.M. from in front of the New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue and 42d Street. Fee: $36. Sponsored by Hasidic Discovery Welcome Center. Reservations and information: (800) 838-9687.  ''HAUNTED GREENWICH VILLAGE'' includes stops at a haunted firehouse, the site of the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire in 1911 and the former location of the Provincetown Playhouse. Sunday at 3:15 P.M. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Fee: $5. Meeting place and reservations: (212) 265-2663.  ''SALUTE TO GEORGE GERSHWIN,'' Manhattan. A walking tour of locations associated with George and Ira Gershwin, including the former Aeolian Hall, where ''Rhapsody in Blue'' was first performed; the old Alvin Theater, where ''Strike Up the Band'' and ''Of Thee I Sing'' played, and Carnegie Hall, site of the world premiere of ''An American in Paris.'' Sunday at noon. Fee: $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Information: (212) 265-2663.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
